Okay, in this section then, let's talk
about the duration estimate, right?
Activity duration estimating and some
estimating methods.
Now this section is primarily going to be
discussing the predictive life cycle.
There's a separate video
where we're going to be talking
about estimating methods
using the agile life cycle.
So this one particularly is about the
predictive life cycle.
Now, a couple of the important terms you
need to understand here.
First of all, what does duration estimate
mean?
Well, as the name suggests, how long
something is going to take, right?
The duration, how long an activity is
going to take, right, how long it'll take
to complete an activity,
or how long it'll take
to complete a work
package and so and so forth.
And the key here is it's a
quantitative assessment,
quantitative meaning that
there's numbers involved.
So, you know, for
example, it'll take three
hours or it'll take three
weeks to do, right?
This activity is going to, you know,
it's a month long.
activity, one month, three weeks,
two hours, these are all numbers,
these are all quantitative values.
As opposed to, for example, a relative
estimate.
In the agile world, we talk about relative
estimating.
But here, since this
video is about predictive,
we'll stick to the predictive terminology.
So it's a quantitative
assessment of actually
how long this particular
activity will take.
Whereas, this other term here,
elapsed time, is basically saying how long
has it actually taken from start to
finish.
And that's going to include stoppage time,
things like lags, and so and so forth.
The actual duration does not consider
lags.
The duration is the actual physical time
to do the work.
The elapsed time is going to include the
total time it has taken, including start
stop and, you know, any lags that you have
in between and so and so forth.
So just a very simple example.
The example that I've
been given, right, we've
been using, building a
house as an example.
So let's just stick with that theme.
So let's just say, you know, we're digging
the foundations and pour in concrete.
And that's going to take us two weeks to
do.
It's going to take us two weeks to dig the
foundations and pour down the concrete.
But then we can't immediately
start the next task of
framing until the concrete
has settled, cured, hardened.
So if it takes one week for the concrete
to cure, to settle, to harden,
then we can't do anything during that one
week.
That is a one week lag.
So the total elapsed time in this case
then will be three weeks.
Two weeks to actually perform the work,
right, dig the foundations and pour the
concrete, and then one week of lag where
we're not actually doing anything.
So the total elapsed time, in that case,
will be three weeks.
The two weeks will be the duration
estimate, right?
The two week will be the actual duration.
Then there's a one week lag.
So the total elapsed time is three weeks.
Now, another important term then is
effort.
An effort then refers to, as it says here,
the number of labour units.
So, for example, this activity will be 10
hours worth of work.
It'll take 10 hours to do this activity.
So let's say we give our team member two
weeks.
So you've got two weeks, we've got a
deadline of two weeks to complete this work.
But it'll only really take them 10 hours
to actually do the work.
Right, they could start and stop.
They could start, you know, do one hour
here, stop the work, then, you know,
start at a later date and do one hour
here, you know, one hour here,
one hour there, half an hour here,
two hours there, until they finish the
work, and the time that
they actually spent on
the activity would have
been about 10 hours.
So level of effort then would be 10 hours.
Although we've given them two weeks to
actually perform the work, if they deliver
it on that deadline, it
means it is taken them, or
rather it means that the
elapsed time is two weeks.
But the actual level of effort,
the actual work that they've done,
is only 10 hours worth of work.
If we were hiring somebody, like an
external consultant or an external
contractor to do the work, we would pay
them for 10 hours.
We would not pay them for two weeks.
We would pay them for 10 hours because
that is the actual level of effort.
Now, there are four
estimating methods that
you need to know about for the PMP exam.
And these are for predictive.
There are four predictive estimating
methods.
So let's talk about each and every one of
these.
So, first one then, analogous, analogous
estimating, also known as top-down, right?
So you can see either of those terms.
You can see analogous estimating or
top-down estimate.
Now, analogous or
top-down is basically saying
that this activity is
similar to a prior activity.
It's using historical information.
And we've done this kind of activity
before, right?
So last time we did this activity,
it was, whatever, 50 hours worth of work.
So there's our analogous estimate.
We performed this activity before,
right, we installed the server, right?
We need to install another server,
right?
It was, you know, let's just say 100 hours
worth of work.
So there's our analogous estimate.
So analogous estimating then, it's quick
and easy, right?
Because it's using
prior similar activity, this
is something similar to
what we've done before.
So it's quick and easy.
However, the disadvantages, it might not
be very accurate.
Just because it took us, whatever,
50, hours last time, it doesn't
necessarily mean it'll take us 50 hours
this time.
There's different technology, for example,
right, we might use different equipment,
we might be using different raw materials,
we might have different team members,
and so on and so and so forth.
There's many factors that's going to
impact it.
So it might not be very accurate,
but it's a ballpark figure.
And that's really what an analogous
estimating is.
It's a quick and easy ballpark figure.
Now, another estimating method, and
remember, again, these are all predicted.
Another estimating method is something
called parametric estimating.
And parametric estimating uses a rule of
thumb or a first principle, uses first
principle mathematics, or a statistical
relationship, right,
to extrapolate results.
You can also use historical
data as well, but you're
always doing some kind of
math with parametric estimating.
So a very simple example here.
If it takes us one hour to lay
down 25 meters a cable, how
long will it take us to lay down
a thousand meters of cable?
So you do the math, and you're going to
come up with 40 hours.
So, I mean, very simple
math here, it takes us 25
meters, sorry, it takes one
hour to lay down 25 meters.
We've got a thousand meters, so 1,000
divided by 25.
It'll take us 40 hours to do this work.
Now, just because it takes us one hour to
lay down 25 meters doesn't necessarily
mean it'll take us 40 hours an entire week
to lay down a thousand meters of cable.
So the advantage generally with parametric
is it can be more accurate than an algus.
However, the disadvantage
is that these parameters
may not scale, like the
example that I just gave here.
Just because it takes us one hour to lay
down 25 meters doesn't necessarily mean
it's going to take us 40 hours to lay down
1,000 meters.
So straight parametric estimating does not
take into consideration things like
learning curves and economies of scale and
so and so forth.
So the same scenario, same example,
same situation, you know, if we could
think, well, if we have five
team members, then this activity
will take us two weeks to
perform with five team members.
So why do we get 10 team members and it'll
only take us one week to perform?
That's not necessarily going to be the
case.
Doubling the number of
resources is not necessarily
going to halve the time
in which to do the work.
So that's the disadvantage of parametric,
right, parametric estimate.
However, in certain situations, though,
parametric can be very accurate, right?
we don't have to deal
with economies of scale
and learning curves and so and so forth.
Now another tool, or another estimating
method, and remember, these are all
estimating methods, right, so for predictive
in this case, bottom-up estimating.
Now, bottom-up estimating is a very,
very detailed estimate.
So it's basically going down to the
granular level.
It's looking at each activity,
you're further analyzing each activity,
right, you're, you're you're breaking each
activity down to your
little sub-activities, right?
And then you're aggregating the results.
You go on, you're rolling up each layer of
the work breakdown structure.
So a bottom-up estimate
out of all of these is
the most accurate, very,
very accurate estimate.
Right, so that's the advantage.
It's very accurate.
But the disadvantage is, it's
time-consuming and therefore expensive.
You can't always do a
bottom-up estimate for
every single activity
or every single project.
And it can only really do a bottom-up when
it's a well-understood project.
If there's a lot of variables,
a lot of unknowns, right, then,
you know, you can't really always do a
bottom-up estimate.
And then the other type, then,
the fourth type then is this one called a
three-point estimate, three-point
estimating.
And there are two types of three-point
You've got something called a triangular
distribution and a beta distribution,
or a pert, which is a weighted average.
So you have a straight average and a
weighted average.
And this is covered in a separate video.
But it uses three values, optimistic,
most likely, and pessimistic.
And based on that, you're going to be
coming up with an average.
It could be a straight average or it could
be a weighted average.
And again, we're going to cover this in a
separate video.
Okay.